Horace Capron Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Horace Capron Papers 1834-1961 1871-1875
MSS15024
Capron, Horace, 1804-1885
1,800 items
6 containers
2.5 linear feet
1 digital file (16.47 MB)
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States army officer and commissioner of agriculture. Correspondence, journals, biographical material, financial records, orders for agricultural equipment and supplies, printed matter, and photographs in physical format as well as a map in both digital and physical format. Relating chiefly to Capron's role as agricultural adviser to the Japanese government in the agricultural development of Hokkaido.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Capron family--Correspondence.; Capron, Horace, 1804-1885.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885--Correspondence.; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872--Correspondence.; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Department of Agriculture.
Subjects
Agriculture--Japan--Hokkaido.; Agriculture--Japan.; Agriculture--United States.
Places
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Occupations
Army officers.; Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Horace Capron, United States army officer and commissioner of agriculture, were given to the Library of Congress by his great-grandson, Banfield Capron, in 1964 and in 1980.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Horace Capron are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Access to digital content is available on-site only in the Manuscript Reading Room and requires advanced notice.
Technical Requirements
The papers of Horace Capron contain a scanned map in JPEG format. The file was created by the Library of Congress using Adobe Photoshop in a Windows operating system, version unknown. The file can be accessed using standard image viewers.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1804, Aug. 31 Born, Attleboro, Mass.
1834 Married Louisa V. Snowden (died 1849)
1836 1851 Owner and superintendent of a cotton factory, Laurel, Md. Became nationally known for progressive farming techniques
1854 Married Margaret Baker
1863 Commander and lieutenant colonel, 14th Illinois Cavalry
1865 Commander and brigadier general, United States Volunteers
1866 Served in United States Army
1867 1871 Commissioner of agriculture
1871 1875 On staff of Agriculture Commission; adviser to the Japanese government
1885, Feb. 22 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Horace Capron (1804-1885) span the years 1834-1961, with the bulk of the material, dating from 1871 to 1875, relating to his experiences as an agricultural adviser to the Japanese government. Capron was given authority to develop the island of Hokkaido, on the northern perimeter of the Japanese Empire, at the time an economic and agricultural frontier. The collection contains journals, correspondence, financial records, maps, and orders for agricultural equipment, livestock, and plants that reflect an early experiment in government planning in agriculture and international cooperation. The papers are in English and Japanese.
Some material relates to Capron's service with the Union army during the Civil War and his work in the 1870s as commissioner of agriculture. The correspondence includes a few letters of Ulysses S. Grant, William T. Sherman, and Horace Greeley.
Also in the collection is correspondence of other members of the Capron family, a handwritten autobiography by Horace Capron, and biographical information.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - General (Box 1)
    - 1834-1866, (17 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1867-1884, undated, (24 folders) (Box 2)
  - Capron family (Box 3)
    - Capron, Albert B., 1868-1900 (Box 3)
    - Capron, Albert S., 1925-1961 (Box 3)
    - Capron, Florence S., 1926-1959 (Box 3)
    - Capron, Horace Mann, 1925-1950 (Box 3)
    - Capron, Margaret (wife), 1864-1890 (Box 3)
    - “C-Y’ miscellaneous, 1851-1878, 1884, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Subject file (Box 3)
  - Civil War, 1862-1864, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Mission to Japan (Box 3)
    - "Expedition to Japan" daily journal, 1871-1875, (1 vol.) (Box 3)
    - "Notes from the Journal of Horace Capron as Advisor & Commissioner under the Japanese Government from 1871 to 1875, Inclusive.", 1896, (1 vol.) (Box 4)
    - "Daily Journal of Horace Capron as Commissioner and Advisor to Kaitakushi or Colonial Department of Japan, 1871-1875", 1925, (1 vol.) (Box 4)
    - Memoranda and receipts, 1871-1874, (4 folders) (Box 4)
- Miscellany (Box 5)
  - Agriculture, Department of, 1865-1870 (Box 5)
  - Articles by Capron, 1848, 1871-1884 (Box 5)
  - Articles by others, 1925, 1937, 1951, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Autobiographical writings, 1882, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Biographical information, 1869-1888, 1938, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Capron, Albert Banfield (father), undated (Box 6)
  - Commissions, appointments, diplomas, and other documents, 1835, 1846, 1863-1871, 1884 (Box 6)
  - Estate file, 1851, 1877 (Box 6)
  - Inventories, Japanese art, 1880-1882 (Box 6)
  - "Lloyd’s Official Map of the State of Tennessee", 1862 (Box 6)
    - Volume, 1862 (Box 6)
    - Scanned map, 2008, mss15024_264_001
  - Photographs, 1871, 1919, 1931 (Box 6)